hi my name is julia silgi i'm a data
scientist and software engineer at r
studio and i'd like to thank um the or
the organizers of the r user group in
korea so much for having me
um today to speak to you
i am so happy to be uh speaking
specifically today about
creating
features for machine learning from text
data
for a couple of reasons
having a better understanding of what we
do to take text data
and then to make it appropriate as an
input for machine learning algorithms
has
many benefits
both if you are directly getting ready
to train a model or if you're at the
beginning of some text analysis project
or if you are trying to understand the
behavior of a model that you're
interacting with some way which is
something that we do in our work as data
scientists or in our
in our daily lives more and more
so when we build models for text either
supervised or unsupervised
we start with something
like this this is some example text data
that i'll use a couple of times during
this talk that um describes some animals
some animals i'm using some text data so
this you know to me as an english
speaker um looks familiar um like i'm i
i um as someone who uses a human
language so i look at this and i can
read it i could speak it aloud and i
understand
i can interpret it what it means
so this kind of data this sort of
natural language data is being generated
all the time
in all kinds of languages
in all kinds of contexts so
whether you work in healthcare
in tech
in finance
basically any kind of organization this
sort of text data is being generated by
um
by customers
by clients by internal stakeholders
inside of a business by people taking
surveys
by
via social media via business processes
and and in all this natural language
there's information
latent in
that text data that can be used to make
better decisions
however
computers are not great at um
at you know looking at this and doing
math on language as it's represented
like this
and instead language has to be
dramatically transformed to some kind of
machine readable numeric representation
that looks more like this what i'm
showing here on the screen to be ready
for almost any kind of model
so i spent a fair amount of time working
on software for people to be able to do
exploratory data analysis
visualization
summarization
tasks like that with text data in a tidy
format where we have one observation per
row
and i love using tidy data principles
for text analysis
especially during those exploratory
phases of an analysis
when it comes time to build a model
often what the underlying
mathematical implementation really needs
is typically something like this
which is a
way to
uh this particular representation is
called the document term matrix so the
exact representation may differ from
what i've shown here
what i have here is we're weighting
things by counts so each each row in
this matrix is a document each
column is a is a word
um a token and the numbers represent
counts how many times does each document
use each word you could weight it in a
different way
using say tf idf instead of counts
or you might keep sequence information
if you're interested in building a deep
learning model but basically for all
kinds of text modeling
from simpler models like naive bayes
models which work well for text
to word embeddings to really the most
state-of-the-art kind of work that's
happening today like transformers for
text data
we have to heavily
feature engineer and process language to
get it to some kind of representation
that's suitable for machine learning
algorithms
so i work on an open source framework in
r
for modeling and machine learning that's
called tidy models and the examples that
i'll be showing today use tidy models
code
some of the specific goals of the tidy
models project are to provide a
consistent flexible framework for real
world modeling practitioners people who
are you know doing their um
that are dealing with real world data
um those who are just starting out to
those who are very experienced in
modeling and
the goal is to harmonize the
heterogeneous
interfaces that exist within r and to
encourage good statistical practice
i'm glad to get to show you some of what
i work on
and build and how we apply it to text
modeling but a lot of what i will talk
about today isn't very specific to tidy
models
or even to r i know this is an r user
group but what we're going to talk about
and focus on are
is a little more conceptual and basic
how do we transform text
into predictors for machine learning
i am excited though to talk about tidy
models and tidy models if you have not
used it before is a meta package
in a similar way that the tidy verse is
a meta package so if you've ever typed
library tidy verse and then you've used
ggplot2 for visualization
d plier for data manipulation
tidy models works in a similar way
um
there are different packages inside of
it that are used for um
different purposes
so the pre-processing or the feature
engineering is part of a broader model
process
you know it that process starts really
with with exploratory data analysis
um
that helps us decide what kind of model
we will build and then it comes to
completion i think i would argue with
model evaluation when you uh you you
measure how well your model performed
tidy models as a piece of software is
made up of our packages each of which
has a specific focus
like
our sample
is for re-sampling uh data to be able to
create um bootstrap free samples
cross-validation resamples all different
kinds of re-samples you might want to
use to
train and evaluate models
the tune package is for hyper parameter
tuning as you might guess from the name
one of these packages is for feature
engineering for a data preprocessing
feature engineering and it is the one
that is called
recipes
so in tidy models we capture this idea
of data pre-processing and feature
engineering in the concept of a
pre-processing recipe that has steps
so you choose
ingredients
or
variables
that you're going to use then you define
the steps
that go into your recipe
then you prepare them using training
data and then you can apply that to any
data set like testing data or new data
at prediction time
so the variables or ingredients that we
use in modeling come in all kinds of
shapes and sizes
including text data
so some of the techniques and approaches
that we use for pre-processing text data
are the same
um as for any other kind of data that
you might use like non-text data uh
numeric data categorical data some for
some of it is the same
but some of what you need to know to be
able to do a good job
of um
in this process for text um is different
and is specific to the nature of what
language data is like
and so i've written a book with my
co-author emile vedfeldt on supervised
machine learning for text analysis and r
and fully the first third of the book
focuses on how we transform
the natural language that we have in
text data into features for modeling
the middle section is about how we use
these features in
simpler or more traditional machine
learning models like regularized
regression or support vector machines
and um
uh then the last third of the book
talks about how we use um deep learning
models with text data so deep learning
models still require these kinds of
transformations from natural language
into um into features for
um
as input for these kinds of models but
deep learning models are
often able to
inherently learn structure of features
from text in ways that those
more traditional or simpler machine
learning models are not
so this book is now complete and
available as of this month as of
november
um folks are getting their first paper
copies and also this book is available
in its entirety at
smalltar.com
so if you're new to dealing with text
data understanding these um these
fundamental pre-processing approaches
for text will set you up for being able
to train effective models
if you're really experienced with text
data if you've dealt with it a lot
already you've probably noticed like we
have
that um that the existing
um
you know resources or literature whether
that's books or tutorials or blog posts
um is is quite sparse when it comes to
um
detailed thoughtful explorations of how
these pre-processing steps work
and how choices made in these feature
engineering steps impact our our model
output
so let's walk through
several of some of these like basic
um
feature engineering approaches and how
they work and what they do
let's start out with
tokenization
so typically one of the first steps in
transfer information from natural
language to machine learning feature
for
really any kind of text analysis
including exploratory data analysis
or building a model anything
is tokenization
in tokenization we take an input some
string some character vector and some
kind of token type
um some meaningful unit of text that
we're interested in like like a word
and we split the input into pieces into
tokens that correspond to the type that
we're interested in
so most commonly the meaningful unit or
type of token that we want to split text
into units of is a word
so this might seem you know
straightforward or obvious but it turns
out it's difficult to clearly define
what a word is for many or even most
languages
so um
so many languages do not use white space
between words at all
which um you know presents a challenge
for tokenization um even languages that
do use white space like like english and
korean
often have particular examples that are
ambiguous
like contractions in english like didn't
which should be um
uh you know maybe more accurately
considered two words um the way the way
particles are used in korean
and how pronouns and negation words are
written in romance languages like
italian and french where they're stuck
together and really maybe they should be
considered two words
once you have figured out what you're
going to do and you make some choices
and you tokenize your text then it's on
its way to being able to be used
in exploratory data analysis or
unsupervised algorithms or as features
for predictive modeling which is what
we're talking about here and what these
results show here so these results are
from a regression model trained on
descriptions of media
from artwork in the tate collection in
the uk
so
what we're predicting in what we are
predicting is when
what year
was um a piece of art created based on
the
the medium that the artwork was created
with and the medium is described with a
little bit of text
so we see here that artwork created
using graphite
watercolor and engraving was more likely
to be created earlier
that though that is more likely to come
from older art and artwork that is
created using
photography
screen point or sorry screen print
screen printing
and and dung
and glitter um are more likely to be
created later there this is more likely
to come from contemporary art uh modern
art
so the the way that um we tokenize this
text
um
you know we started with natural human
generated texts of people writing out
the descriptions of the the media
that these art pieces of art were
created with
and the way we tokenized that natural
human generated text that we started
with has a big impact on what we learned
from it if we tokenized in a different
way
um we would have gotten different
results um in terms of performance like
how
accurately we were able to predict
predict the year and also in terms of
how we interpret the model like what is
it that we're able to learn from it
so this is one kind of tokenization to
the single word but we also
we all another way to tokenize instead
of breaking up into single words or
unigrams we can tokenize to n grams
so an n gram is a continuous sequence of
n items from a given sequence of texts
so this shows that same piece of little
bit of text i'm describing this animal
divided up into bi-grams or n-grams of
two tokens so notice how the words in
the bi-grams overlap
so the word collard
appears in both of the first bigrams the
collared
collared peccary peccary also also
referred referred to so engram
tokenization slides along the text to
create overlapping sets of tokens
this shows trigrams for the same thing
um so using unigrams um one word is
faster and more efficient but we don't
capture information about word order
i'm using a higher value for n you know
two or three or even more
um keeps keeps this
more complex information about word
order and concepts
um
that are described in multi-word
phrases
but the vector space of tokens
increases dramatically
that corresponds to a reduction in token
counts we don't count each token as very
many times and that means depending on
your particular data set
you might not be able to get good
results
so combining different degrees of
engrams can allow you to extract
different levels of detail from text so
unigrams
can tell you which individual words have
been used a lot of times
um and some of those words might be
overlooked
in bigram or trigram crowns if they
don't co-appear
with other words as often
this plot compares model performance for
a lasso regression model predicting the
year of supreme court opinions the
united states supreme court opinions um
with three different degrees of engrams
what we're doing here is we are taking
the text of the writings of the united
states supreme court and we're
predicting
um
when when did it when was that text
written so can we predict how old a
piece of text is from the contents of
the text
so holding uh the number of tokens
constant at a thousand
using unigrams alone
performs best for this corpus of um
opinions from the united states supreme
court
this is not always the case depending on
the kind of model you use the data set
itself we might see the best performance
combining unigrams and diagrams or maybe
some other
option
in this case if we wanted to incorporate
some of that more complex information
that we have in the bigrams and the
trigrams we probably would need to
increase the number of
tokens in the model quite a bit
so keep in mind when you look at results
like these that identifying engrams is
computationally expensive
um and this is especially compared to
the
amount of like a model the improvement
in model performance that we often see
like if we
if we see some you know modest
improvement by adding in bigrams it's
important to keep in mind how much
improvement we see relative to
how long it takes to
identify bigrams and then train that
model so for example for this data set
of supreme court opinions where we held
the number of tokens constant so the
model training had the same number of
tokens in it
um
using bigrams plus unigrams takes twice
as long to train
to do the feature engineering and the
training than only unigrams and adding
in trigrams as well takes almost five
times as long as training on unigrams
alone so this is a computationally
expensive thing to do
going in the other direction
um we can tokenize to units smaller than
words so like these are what are called
character shingles
so um we take words
the collared peccary
and we can instead of looking at words
we can go down and look at sub word
information there's multiple different
ways to break words up into sub words
that are appropriate for machine
learning
and often these kinds of um approaches
or algorithms have the benefit of being
able to encode
unknown uh or new words
um
at prediction time so when it when it's
time to make a prediction on new data
it's not it's not uncommon for there to
be new vocabulary words at that time and
if we didn't see them in the training
data you know what are we going to do
about those new words when we um train
using sub word information often we can
handle those new words if we saw the sub
word
in our training data set
so
using this kind of sub word information
is a way to incorporate morphological
sequences into our models of you know
various kinds of
this is something that applies to
uh you know
various languages not just english
so these results are for a
classification model with a data set of
very short texts it's just the names of
post offices in the united states so
super short
and the goal of the model was to predict
did the um
did the po is the post office located in
hawaii
in the middle of the pacific ocean or is
it located in the rest of the united
states
so i created features for the model that
are
sub words of these post office names um
and we end up learning that the names
that start with h and p or contain that
ale
sub word are more likely to be in hawaii
and the sub words a and d
and ri and ing
are are
more likely to come from the post office
that are outside of hawaii
so this is an example of how we
tokenized differently and we're able to
learn something
new we're able to learn something
different
so in tidy models we collect all these
kinds of decisions about tokenization
and code that looks like this
so we start with a recipe that specifies
what
variables or ingredients that we'll use
and then we define these preprocessing
steps so even at this first
and arguably you know simple and basic
step the choices that we make affect our
modeling results in a big way
the next pre-processing um step that i
want to talk about is
stop words
so once we have split text
into um tokens we often find that not
all words carry the same amount of
information if maybe any information at
all actually for a machine learning task
so common words that carry little or
perhaps no meaningful information are
called stuff words
so this is one of the stop word lists
that's available for
korean so it's common advice and
practice to um
to say hey just remove just remove
remove these stop words for um for a lot
of
natural language processing tasks
what i'm showing here
is the entirety of one of the shorter
english stop word lists that's used
really broadly so you know it's words
like
um
i
me my pronouns conjunctions and of the
and these are you know very common words
that are not considered super important
the decision though to just remove stop
words is often more involved and
perhaps more fraught than what you'll
than what you'll find reflected in a lot
of resources that are out there
so almost all the time uh real world nlp
practitioners use pre-made stop word
lists
so this plot visualizes
set intersections for three common stop
word lists in english
in what is called an upset plot
so the three lists are called the
snowball list smart and the iso list
so um you can see the the lengths of the
list are represented by the length of
the bars and then we see the
intersections which words are in common
on these lists by the by the vertical
bars so the lengths of the list are
quite different
and also notice they don't all contain
the same sets of words
the important thing to remember about
stop word lexicons
is that they
they are not created in some
neutral perfect setting
but instead
they are
um they are context specific
um
they they can be biased uh both of these
things are true because they are lists
created from large data sets of language
so they reflect
the characteristics of the data used in
their creation
so this is
the ten words that are in the english
language smart lexicon but not in the
english snowball lexicon
so notice that they're all contractions
but that's not because the snowball
exchange doesn't include contractions it
has a lot of them
also notice that it has
um
that she's
is on this list and so that means that
that list has he's but it does not have
the list she's
so this is an example of that of that
bias i mentioned that occurs because
these lists are created from large data
sets of text
lexicon creators look at the most
frequent words in some big corpus of
language they make a cut off
and then some decisions about what to
include or
exclude uh you know
based you know on the list that they
have and you end up here so because
um in many large data sets of language
you have more representat more you know
representation of um
of of of men um you end up with a
situation like this where a stop word
list will have he's but not she's
so many decisions when it comes to
modeling or analysis with language
we as practitioners have to decide
what is appropriate for our particular
domain
it turns out this is even true when it
comes to picking a stop word list
so in tidy models we can implement a
pre-processing step
like removing stop words
by adding an additional step to our
recipe so first we specified what
variables we would use then we tokenized
the text and now we are removing
stop words here using just the default
step since we are not passing in any
other arguments we could though
use a non-default step or even a custom
list if that was most appropriate to our
domain
this plot compares the model performance
for predicting the year
of um
that same data set of
supreme court opinions with three
different stopward lexicons of different
lengths
so the snowball lexicon contains the
smallest number of words and in this
case it results in the best performance
so removing fewer stop words results in
the best performance here so this
specific result is not generalizable to
all data sets and contexts but the fact
that removing different sets of stop
words can have noticeably different
effects on your model um that is quite
transferable so the only way to know
what is the best thing to do is to try
several options and see so machine
learning in general right is a is a
empirical
this is an empirical field right like we
don't know
we don't often have reasons a priori to
know what will be the best thing to do
and so typically we have to
try a different option to see what will
be the best thing
all right then the the third
[Music]
pre-processing step that i want to talk
about
for text is
stemming
so when we deal with text often
documents contain different versions of
one base word um often called a stem
so what
if say for an english example say if we
aren't interested in the difference
between animals
plural
and animal
singular and we want to treat them both
together
so that idea is at the heart of stemming
so there's no one
right way or correct way to stem text so
this plot shows three approaches for
stemming in english
starting from hey let's just remove a
final s
um to more complex rules about plural
handling plural endings uh that middle
one it is called the s summer
um it's a set of it's like a little set
of rules
and and that last one is the best known
one probably the best-known
implementation of stemming in english
called the porter algorithm
so you can see here that porter stemming
is the most different from the other two
in the top 20 words here from the data
set of animal descriptions that i've
been using we see how the word species
was treated differently
animal predator
this sort of
collection of words
live living life lives that was treated
differently
so practitioners are typically
interested in stemming text data because
it buckets
tokens together that we believe
belong belong together in in a way that
we understand that as um as human users
of language
so we can use uh approaches like this
which um
which are pretty um like step-by-step
rules based this is typically called
stemming um or and it's fairly
algorithmic in nature like um
first do this then do this then do this
or you can use lemmatization
um
which is usually based on large
dictionaries
of words and it incorporates uh like a
linguistic understanding of what words
belong together
so most of the existing approaches for
this kind of tax task in korean
are
are limited lemmatizers based on these
dictionaries and that are trained
um
using large data sets of language
so this seems like it's going to be a
helpful thing to do
when you hear about this you're like oh
yeah sounds sounds good sounds smart
especially because
with text data we are typically
overwhelmed with features with um tokens
with numbers of tokens
like we this is typically the situation
when we're dealing with text data text
data so here we have this um
this and these animal description data
and i made a matrix representation of it
like we would typically use in some
machine learning algorithm
and look how many features there are
000 almost 17 000 features
um
that that's the number of features that
would be going into
the um the model look at the sparsity
98 percent sparse that's high very
sparse data so this is the sparsity of
the data that will go into the machine
learning algorithm to build our
supervised machine learning model
if we stem the words
if i use here an approach for stemming
we reduce the number of word features by
many thousands
the sparsity unfortunately did not
change as much but we reduced the number
of features by a lot by bucketing those
words together that our stemming
algorithm
um say belong together so you know
common sense says
reducing the number of words features
so dramatically is going to
perform
improve the performance of our machine
learning model
but that is that does assume that we
have not lost any important information
by by stemming
and it turns out that stemming or
limitization
can often be very helpful in some
contexts but the typical algorithms used
for these
um are somewhat aggressive
and they have been built to favor
sensitivity
or recall
or the true positive rate
and
this is at the expense of the
specificity or the precision or the true
negative rate so in a supervised machine
learning context what this does is this
affects a mod a model's um
positive predictive
value the pres the precision or its
ability to um
to not incorrectly label true negatives
as positive
i hope i got that right um
so you know to make this more concrete
stemming can increase a model's ability
to find the positive examples
of say the animal descriptions that are
associated with say a certain diet if
that's what we're modeling however if
text is over stemmed
the resulting model loses its ability to
label the negative examples
say the descriptions that are not about
that diet that's what we're looking for
and this can be a real challenge when
training models with text data kind of
finding that that balance there because
often we don't we often we don't have a
dial that we can change on these
stemming on these stemming algorithms
so even just very basic pre-processing
for text like what i'm showing here in
this feature engineering recipe can be
computationally expensive
and the choices that a practitioner
makes like whether or not to remove stop
words or to stem text can have dramatic
impact on how machine learning models
of all kinds perform whether those are
simpler models
more traditional machine learning models
or deep learning models
what this means is that
the the price the prioritization that we
as practitioners give to like learning
teaching and writing about feature
engineering steps for text really
contributes to better more robust
statistical practice in our field
i mentioned before the sparsity of text
data and i want to come back to that
because it is one of text data's really
defining characteristics
because of just how
language works
we use um a few words a lot of times
and then a lot of words only just a
couple of times only a few a few times
and with a real set of natural language
you end up with relationships that look
like this that look like these plots in
terms of how the sparsity changes as you
add more documents
and more unique words to a corpus
so the sparsity goes up real fast as you
add more unique words and the memory
that is required to handle
um
uh
you know this this set of documents goes
up very fast
so even if you use specialized data
structures
meant to store sparse data like sparse
matrices you still end up growing the
memory required to handle these data
sets in a very
non-linear way it still grows up very
fast so this means it can take a very
long time to train your model or even
that um
you you know you you outgrow the memory
available on your machine you have to go
to the cloud to an expensive you know
big memory situation this can be a real
challenge
and this challenge it um
is what has behind the motivating
of um vector
languages for models
so
linguists have worked for a long time
on vector languages for models that can
reduce the number of dimensions
representing text data
based on how people use language
so this quote here
goes all the way back to 1957.
so the idea here
is that yeah we use
like the the data is very sparse you
know but we don't use words um
randomly it's not independent the words
are not used independently of each other
but rather there's relationships that
exist between how words are used
together
and we can use those relationships to
create
to transform our sparse high dimensional
space into a special
dense
low dimensional space well lower lower
we still still has like 100 100
dimensions but much lower than the like
many thousands
uh hundreds tens hundreds of thousands
of space so the idea here we use
statistical modeling
maybe just um
uh word counts plus matrix factorization
maybe fancier math that involves neural
networks to take this really high
dimensional space and we create a new
lower dimensional lower dimensional
space that is special because the new
space is created based on vectors that
incorporate information
about which words are used together so
you shall know a word by the company it
keeps
so you need a big data set of text to
create or learn these kinds of word
vectors or word embeddings
so this table that i'm showing right now
it's from a set of embeddings that i
created using a um
a data set or a corpus of complaints
complaints to the united states
consumer
financial protection bureau
so this is a government body in the
united states where people can complain
and say
what is wrong with something to do with
a financial product like like a credit
card
a mortgage a student loan
something to do with like a financial
product they're like something went
wrong with my credit card something went
wrong with my mortgage that company is
not being fair so you come and you
complain to it
um so i took all those complaints um and
built a
a so it's our high dimensional space and
build a low dimensional space
and we can look in that space and
understand
um what words are related to each other
in this space so in the new space
defined by the embeddings the word month
is closest to words like year
months plural
monthly
installments payment so these are words
that are um that makes sense in the
context of
financial products like credit cards or
mortgages
in the new space defined by these
embeddings
the word error is closest to the words
like mistake
clerical like a clerical mistake
problem glitch oh there was a glitch on
my
mortgage statement
so we see these kinds of uh
or miscommunication misunderstanding you
know like these are these are words that
are used in similar ways
so
you don't have to create embeddings
yourself
because it requires quite a lot of data
to make them so you can use word
embeddings that are pre-trained
i.e created by someone else
based on some huge corpus of data that
they have access to and you probably
don't
so let's look at one of those data sets
let's look at
this table shows the results for the
same word error
but for the glove embeddings so the
glove embeddings are a set of
pre-trained embeddings that are created
based on a very large data set that's
like
all of wikipedia
all of the google news data set
um
just just like
huge swaths of the internet have been
fed in to create these embeddings
so some of the closest words
here are similar
to those that are before but we no
longer have some of that domain specific
flavor like clerical discrepancy
and now we have um or like
miscommunication you know but and now we
have um calculation and probability
which people were not talking about with
their financial product complaints
so this really highlights um
how these how these work um here before
we we created our own and we were able
to learn relationships that were
specific to this context and here we go
to the to a more general set that that
was learned somewhere else
so embeddings are trained or learned
from a large corpus of text data and the
characteristics of that corpus become
part of the embeddings
so machine learning in general you know
is exquisitely sensitive to whatever it
is that's in your training data and this
is never more obvious than when um
dealing with text data
and and perhaps with word embeddings is
just like one of these classic examples
where this is true
it turns out that um
this this shows up
in how any human
um prejudice or bias in the corpus
becomes imprinted
into the embeddings
so in fact when we look at some of these
most commonly available embeddings that
are out there
bias is um
we we see that um
african-american first names that are
more common for african americans in the
united states they're associated with
more unpleasant feelings than european
american first names in these embedding
spaces
women's first names are more associated
with family
and men's first names are more
associated with career
and terms associated with women are more
associated with the arts and terms
associated with men are more associated
with science
so
it turns out actually bias is so
ingrained in word embeddings that the
word embeddings themselves can be used
to quantify change
in um
in social attitudes over time
so word embeddings are
maybe an exaggerated or extreme example
but it turns out that all the feature
engineering decisions that we make when
it comes to text data have a significant
effect on our results
both in terms of the model performance
that we see
and also in terms of how appropriate or
fair our models are
so given all that when it comes to
pre-processing your text data
creating these features that you need
you have a lot of options and quite a
bit of responsibility so my advice is
always start with simpler models that
you can understand quite deeply
be sure to adopt good statistical
practices as you train and tune your
models so you aren't
you aren't fooled about model
performance improvements
when you try different approaches
and also to use model explainability
tools and frameworks so you can
understand any less straightforward
models that you try
so my co-workers and i have written
about all of these topics um and how to
use them with tidy models if that's what
you like to use and we will continue to
do so
with that i will say
thank you so very much and i want to be
sure to again
thank the um
thank the organizers of the r user group
in korea i want to thank my teammates on
the tidy models team at our studio as
well as my co-author
emil v veldt